# Sachin S. Pukale

# Career Summary

With 8 years of wide experience in business development, technology consulting, product design & engineering of complex embedded systems, I have gained a well-defined understanding of the business-technology interface and capacity to identify and align clients' emerging technology needs with products and services.

In my present role, I'm involved in business development for defence platforms (electro-mechanical-hydraulic products) & services and am responsible for maintaining strong relationships with key international accounts, as well as developing new contacts and relationships. Ongoing interaction and business opportunities are from diverse customers & countries such as USA, Canada, UK, France, Germany, Israel, South Korea, Indonesia and Algeria. I also keep a close eye on market trends and identify gaps and niches that represent new business opportunities. This involves continual business prospecting, bidding and maintaining pipeline management. In my preceding roles, I was involved in technology consulting for Electro Optical Infrared Systems, a niche high technology area in Indian defence market. I also have experience of design, engineering & project management of complex systems such as micro controller, PLC & HMI based electro mechanical control system panel & sub systems for various projects.

Diverse background spanning product development, project management, technology consulting & marketing and businessdevelopment disciplines underscores expertise in engaging decision makers and devising winning sales strategies and solutions.

# Professional Experience

# LARSEN & TOUBRO LIMITED, HEAVY ENGINEERING IC - MUMBAI

Customers: International Defence & Aerospace Companies, Indian & International Ministry of Defence, DRDO, Defence PSU's.

## Asst Manager - International Business Development

[11/2012 – Present]

Interaction with senior management of global defence & aerospace companies, government agencies and offshore representative for new business development and lead generation for defence platforms. Key account management of international representatives/customers, national defence forces and R&D establishments. Keep a close eye on market trends and identify opportunities to offer solutions to customer. Proactively work with customers to assist them formulating RFP documents.

Understanding RFP/RFI requirements, bid management with technology and engineering centers for technical proposal & transfer price, prepare commercial bid documents. Collaboration with International defence contractors for strategic products and offset business. NDA, MOU, Teaming agreements formulation & execution with the help of legal teams.

Projects: Engineering & Bridging Systems, Air Defence Fire Control Radar, Self Propelled Air Defence Gun Missile System, etc.

List of global companies: USA: Raytheon, L-3 | Germany: Cassidian, Atlas Electronik | UK: Chess Dynamics | France: Dassault, Sagem, Thales, Nexter | Israel: IAI, Elbit Systems, Controp, Rafael | South Korea: Samsung, Doosan, etc.

#### Technical Consultant - Electro Optical Infrared (EO/IR) System

[06/2010 - 10/2012]

Closely monitor changes in Infrared technology & sensors, continuously upgrade know-how-why and incorporate latest technology in new system designs. Interact with internal & external end customers to carry out technical marketing & devising RFP requirements. RFQ preparation & tendering to global EO/IR Suppliers, bid management, techno-commercial evaluation, negotiations and selection of EO/IR supplier. Provide technical support till final integration & environmental qualification. Extend consulting support to other BU's and IC's of L&T.

Under new product initiative, presented a comprehensive Business Plan to Board Members of L&T HE IC for EO/IR Systems. Business plan was selected among top two and has been positioned to further develop & add EO/IR products into L&T's defence portfolio. When implemented annual business revenue of ~50 Cr is expected within 2 years.

Projects: Thermal Imaging Fire Control System for T72 Tank, Interceptor Boats, Zu-23 AD Gun Upgrade, Nag Missile Carrier, Persistent Surveillance Systems, Futuristic Infantry Combat Vehicle, Self Propelled 155mm/52Cal Artillery Gun System, etc.

Sachin S. Pukale – Business Development Manager

Detailed study of technical requirements of electro mechanical system from RFP, preparing transfer price & technical bid documents for marketing & business development teams. Conceptualization of complex system into subsystems/modules. Preparation of sub-system level electrical schematics, GUI/HMI layouts, control panel/module drawings, design documents, etc. Coordinating design activity between software, hardware, mechanical and documentation teams. Preparing system level test plans, assembly, integration & testing of complete system. Performing system level ESS & EMI/EMC qualification. Performing successful FAT with customer. Lead team of 3-4 engineers.

Projects: L/70 Upgrade, Revathi Radar Stabilizer, Advance Air Defence Missile Launcher.

## TATA POWER COMPANY LIMITED, STRATEGIC ELECTRONICS DIVISION - MUMBAI

Customer Profile: DRDO, Indian Ministry of Defence

### Executive Engineer - Embedded System Design

[09/2005 - 05/2008]

Worked on microcontroller based embedded system design for strategic applications. Responsible for conceptualization and designing of electronic assemblies, generate circuit schematics, critical parameter verification by circuit simulation, design reports generation, writing application specific firmware/driver for embedded system. Interacted with the various departments such as mechanical department for packaging, QC for quality checks, vendors for the PCB Gerber design, development and manufacturing of electronic assembly, procurement of components. Performing ESS & EMI/EMC qualification at sub-system level.

Projects: Universal Rocket Launch System, PINAKA Multi Barrel Rocket Launcher, Automatic Test Equipment, etc.

### Education

## SARDAR PATEL COLLEGE OF ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF MUMBAI

# B. E. Electronics Engineering [08/2001 - 05/2005]

60.63%

#### Final Year Project - Project Leader

Designed an autonomous microcontroller based robot 'Intelligent Path Finder –I' to do the pick and place operation along with autonomous maneuvering on grid maze. Final year project received financing from TCS & Accenture.

#### Other Undergraduate Projects

- Designed 'Stepper Motor Controller' using a micro controller (2003)
- Designed '4-Bit Arithmetic and logic Unit 'using VHDL (2003)

# Trainings Undertaken

- 11/2012: Capstone® Business Simulation (complex *business simulation* designed to teach strategy, competitive analysis, finance, cross-functional alignment, and the selection of tactics)
- 08/2011 : Finance for Non-Finance
- 08/2007: Digital Signal Processor and Applications at IIT, Madras
- 03/2004 to 06/2004: Embedded System Design and Applications Course at SPCE, Mumbai
- 02/2003 to 07/2003: VLSI Design with VHDL Course at SPCE, Mumbai

#### Achievements

- 1st Prize in Western region: Represented L&T team in 35th National Competition for AIMA Young Managers, at Mumbai on 10-11 July 2009
- Semifinalist: Lead SPCE college team in 'DD-MIT Robocon 2005', a National Robotics Competition held at Maharashtra Institute of Technology, Pune
- 2<sup>nd</sup> Prize 'Yantra-yudha' ideas'04, CSI National Student Convention, Mumbai
- 3rd Prize for article in Electronics Student Association (ESA) magazine eSpark 2004 at SPCE, Mumbai

## Extracurricular Activities

- 2012: Assisted ex-L&T colleague to start & establish company in Home Automation segment
- 2010: Process Lead for Project Planning area of CMM level 3 certification at L&T Defence Technology Center
- 2009: Conducted a seminar on emerging HMI & Display Technologies at L&T Defence Technology Center
- 2006: Part of Cultural Committee at TPCL, SED in 2006
- 2004: Conducted workshop on 'Making of Autonomous Robotics' for 'IEEE Brainwaves' student chapter in DJ Sanghvi College of Engineering, Mumbai for 2nd and 3rd year students of engineering
- 2004: Active part of Management (Tech-team) in event 'SPACE 2004' held at Sardar Patel College of Engineering, Mumbai
- 2004: Active part of Tech-team in event 'Techno Beak 2004' held at Sardar Patel College of Engineering, Mumbai
- 2002: Volunteered for Administrative Team in event 'SPACE 2002' held at Sardar Patel College of Engineering, Mumbai

# Interpersonal Skills

Leadership, quick on job learner, business networking, like to study complex systems and good team player

#### Interests

Intra preneurship, general business reading and listening to music

## Additional Information

Date of Birth : 07 May 1984Marital Status : Married

- Passport : F5619833, Valid Through: 24 November 2015

- References : Yes, on request.